IP address... พวกมันอย่างกับเวทมนตร์เลยล่ะ
พวกมันทำให้อินเตอร์เน็ตใช้งานได้
และนั่นคือสาเหตุว่าทำไม
สิ่งของแทบทุกอย่างในบ้านผมถึงมี IP address
โทรศัพท์ของผม นาฬิกา หลอดไฟ
เตาอบ รถยนต์
ลูก ๆ ของผม ส้วมของผม
เอ่อ.. จริง ๆ ก็ยังไม่มีหรอก
บอกตามตรงนะ ไม่ได้อยากมาจับส้วมให้แบบนี้เลย
แต่ว่าอะไรคือ IP address แล้วอะไรที่ทำให้มันเวิร์คกันล่ะ?
มาคุยเรื่องนั้นกันดีกว่าครับ
เอาจริงแล้ว
นี่คือคลิปแรกของซีรีส์ที่ผมจะเรียกว่า "คุณอ่อนเรื่อง subnetting"
เพราะเราทุกคนก็ค่อนข้างจะอ่อนเรื่อง subnetting ซักนิดใช่ไหมล่ะครับ?
และในซีรีส์นี้เราจะเริ่มต้นด้วยคำว่า
"เห้ย... IP Address มันคืออะไรวะ"
ซึ่งเป็นเรื่องที่เราจะพูดถึงกันในวันนี้
และเมื่อจบหลักสูตรแล้ว คุณจะได้สกิลนินจาจอมยุทธ์สาขา subnetting
หรืออะไรก็ตามที่อยากเรียกไปครอง
คุณจะต้องเก่งในการทำ subnetting
นั่นแหละคือเป้าหมายของผม
และถ้าเกิดว่าคุณยังไม่รู้
การทำความเข้าใจเรื่อง IP addressing และ subnetting เนี่ย
เป็นเหมือนทักษะที่จำเป็นสำหรับทุกเรื่องใน IT เลย
แบบว่า ในทุกอาชีพเลย การทำระบบเครือข่าย
การแฮ็กอย่างมีจริยธรรม ระบบความปลอดภัย คลาวด์
ทุกเรื่องมี IP Address เป็นส่วนอยู่ในนั้น
และรวมถึง Subnet อันโอชะของเราด้วย
This video is also part of my CCNA
series, sponsored by boon software.
If you wanna get your CCNA or your CCMP
two of the best it certifications in the
world, boon is what you want to use from
courseware to labs to practice exams.
They have you covered. They'll
get you prepped and ready.
I personally use boon to pass my
t-shirt exam, which is very, very hard.
Cisco networking exam and boon
was amazing. And not to mention,
they have a great amount
of content on subnetting.
So as you're watching this
video and this series,
and you wanna get extra
practice, dude, check out boon.
And it's not just CCNA and
CC and P they have security.
Plus they've got C H all kinds
of stuff. They have the best,
like I'm not kidding the best practice
exams in the industry. So if you're like,
yeah, yeah, I'm not sure if I'm gonna
pass security. Plus they'll tell you,
try their practice exam. And
they'll tell you, anyways,
IP หรือ Internet Protocol Address
มันก็คล้าย ๆ กับเบอร์โทรศัพท์
ที่เรากำหนดให้กับอุปกรณ์แต่ละชิ้นนี่แหละครับ
อย่างถ้าส้วมของผมต้องการส่งข้อความไปหา
Apple Watch ว่าผมเป็นไงอยู่ในห้องน้ำมั่ง
มันสามารถทำได้แน่นอน เพราะพวกมันมีช่องทางในการสื่อสารหากันครับ
พวกมันมีสิ่งที่คล้ายกับเบอร์โทรศัพท์
เราใช้เบอร์โทรศัพท์ในการส่งข้อความหากัน
แต่พวกอุปกรณ์เนี่ยไม่ใช่ครับ พวกมันใช้ IP address
และแน่นอนว่ามีข้อแตกต่างนิดหน่อยอยู่แหละ
แล้วเราจะมาดูกันว่ามันทำงานกันประหลาดขนาดไหน
แต่ตอนนี้รู้ไว้ก่อนก็พอว่าถ้าไม่มี IP address
พวกมันก็คุยกันไม่ได้
เราถึงต้องกำหนดให้มัน
มันคือสิ่งที่เปิดให้มีช่องทางการสื่อสารกัน
และยังไม่ได้พูดถึงเรื่องที่ว่า มันสามารถทำให้
อุปกรณ์ต่าง ๆ ของเราเชื่อมต่ออินเตอร์เน็ตได้ด้วย
ทุกคนต้องอยากให้ทุกอย่างมาเชื่อมต่อกับส้วมของเราได้
อยู่แล้วใช่ไหมล่ะ? เอ้อ!
เพราะงั้นตอนนี้เรารู้แล้วนะว่าถ้าอุปกรณ์นึงต้องการคุยกับอีกอุปกรณ์
มันจำเป็นต้องมี IP Address
ซึ่งนั่นหมายความว่าอุปกรณ์ที่คุณใช้
ดูวิดีโอของผมอยู่ตอนนี้เนี่ย
มันก็มี IP Address เพราะมันกำลังคุยกับ YouTube
แล้ว YouTube ก็ตอบกลับมาเช่นกัน
มาหา IP Address ของคุณกันเถอะครับ
ไม่ว่าคุณจะใช้อะไร เราก็มีทางหามัน
บน Windows เราจะใช้โปรแกรมที่มีชื่อว่า
CMD หรือ command prompts
ลองไปเสิร์ชหาแล้วเปิดดูนะครับ
ส่วนบน Mac และ Linux มันจะเป็นสิ่งที่เรียกว่า Terminal
ให้ใช้โปรแกรมนั้นนะครับ
สำหรับโทรศัพท์และอุปกรณ์อื่นๆ
อีกเดี๋ยวผมจะโชว์ให้คุณดูเอง บน Windows
เข้ามาแล้วให้พิมพ์ว่า ipconfig
คำเดียว แค่นั้นเลย เสร็จแล้วกดปุ่ม Enter
ส่วนบน Linux พิมพ์ว่า ifconfig
แค่คำเดียว กดปุ่ม Enter
ส่วนบนโทรศัพท์ของคุณ ให้เข้าไปในแอปตั้งค่า
เข้าไปในหน้า wifi กดตาม UI ไป แล้วคุณจะเจอ
นี่ไง IP address ของคุณ และถ้ากลับมาดู
ที่ Windows นี่คือ IP Address ของคุณ
ชื่อมันบ่งบอกเลยว่าเป็น IPv4 Address ทางซ้ายนี้
แต่อย่าไปสับสนกับคำว่า v4 นะครับ
ช่างมันไปก่อน ตอนนี้มาคุยเรื่อง
IP Address เจ้ากรรมของเรากันดีกว่า
ไอ้หมอนี่มันหน้าตาแปลกๆ แถมยังดูโคตรยากอีก
มันคือเลขอะไรไม่รู้มาเรียงกัน
คั่นด้วยจุดสามจุด
แค่นั้นก็แปลกพอแล้ว
แล้วเรายังมีไอ้หมอนี่ แล้วก็ไอ้หมอนี่อีก
พวกมันมาทำอะไรกัน?
ก็ ง่าย ๆ เลยพวกมันคือเหล่าเพื่อนรัก
ของเจ้า IP Address นี่แหละครับ
เราจะพูดถึงสองตัวนี้ในอีกไม่นาน มาดูเจ้าหมอนี่กันดีกว่า
นาย Subnet Mask
อย่างน้อยก็เป็นชื่อเรียกใน Windows ที่เราใช้อยู่
ถ้าเป็นใน Mac หรือ Linux
คุณอาจจะเจอคำว่า netmask แทน ก็คืออันเดียวกันนี่แหละ
ส่วนสำหรับเจ้านี้
มันคือคุณหญิง Default Gateway
ซึ่งอาจจะมีชื่ออื่น ๆ เช่น Default Router หรือแค่
Router เลยก็ได้ สำหรับแก๊งนี้ก็ประมาณนี้แหละครับ
มาพูดถึงดาวเด่นของเรากันดีกว่า
ไอ้หนูที่เราสนใจ เจ้า IP Address
โดยมาเริ่มจากว่า
หมอนี่มันมาได้ยังไงก่อน?
แล้วอุปกรณ์ของคุณเอาเลขพวกนี้มาจากไหน?
ใครเป็นคนให้กับไอ้หนูนี่? มันปลอดภัยไหม?
ใครเป็นคนมอบเลขพวกนี้ให้กับอุปกรณ์ของคุณ?
ซึ่งเอาจริงแล้วนั่นเป็นคำถามที่ดีนะครับ
เพราะบางครั้งเราสามารถได้ IP Address ที่ไม่ดีได้
ไว้สำหรับคลิปอื่นละกัน
เอาล่ะ ถ้าอย่างนั้นอุปกรณ์ของคุณเอา IP Address มาจากไหน?
มันตกลงมาจากท้องฟ้ารึเปล่า?
อืม ก็ประมาณนั้นแหละ ถ้าคุณใช้ wifi น่ะนะ
จะเห็นว่าไม่ว่าจะเป็นบ้านของคุณ
หรือไม่ว่าจะที่ไหนก็ตาม
เรามีสิ่งนี้ที่เรียกว่าเราเตอร์ มันอาจจะดูคุ้นตา
อาจจะซ่อนอยู่ในลิ้นชักคุณก็ได้
ใต้ดงเสื้อกันหนาวที่คุณเก็บไว้ใส่เดือนธันวา
ซึ่งบอกตามตรงนะครับ ไปช่วยชีวิตมันเถอะ
เอาเสื้อกันหนาวพวกนั้นออกไป
เขาก็ต้องหายใจเหมือนกัน ข้างในนั้นมันร้อนนะ
เราเตอร์เนี่ยคือคุณปัญญา นิรันดร์กุลของเหล่า IP address
ทุก ๆ ครั้งที่มีอุปกรณ์เชื่อมต่อกับระบบเครือข่ายของคุณ
เขาจะบอกว่า เห้ยนี่
นี่คือ IP Address นี่คือ IP Address
สำหรับคุณ สำหรับคุณ และสำหรับคุณ
ทุกคนได้ IP Address ไป
ซึ่งศาสตร์มืดที่ชื่อว่า DHCP คือกระบวนการที่อยู่เบื้องหลัง
ที่ทำให้มีการแจก IP ได้
ถ้าคุณอยากรู้เพิ่มเติมว่ามันทำงานยังไง
เราจะมาพูดถึงเรื่องนั้นกันทีหลัง
แต่สิ่งที่สำคัญคือ คุณปัญญาเป็นให้ IP Address กับอุปกรณ์ของคุณ
นั่นคือประเด็นที่ผมอยากให้คุณได้กลับไปนะ จดลงไปซะ
โอเค ทีนี้กลับมาดูที่เจ้า IP Address
ผมขอถามอะไรหน่อยสิ
ผมรู้ได้ยังไงว่า IP Address ของคุณเริ่มต้นด้วยเลข 192.168.1
คือส่วนใหญ่แล้วนั่นคือ IP Address ของพวกคุณใช่ไหมล่ะ? ช่างน่ากลัว
Especially since each of these numbers
can be any number between zero and two to
55. So your IP address could
be ten three, two, one,
or it could even be 1, 2, 3, 4.
So why is it that most of your IP
addresses start with 1 92, 1 68 1?
Well, there's a lot of reasons actually,
that I'm not gonna go into because
it does get pretty complicated,
but the short and easy
answer is that it's Oprah.
Oprah decided that that's what your IP
address should be, should start with.
It always comes back to Oprah.
And the way that Oprah tells us that
each IP address in your network in your
house is gonna start with 1 92, 1 6,
8. One is through Mr. Subnet mask.
I told you, come gonna play
here in a bit. Here he is.
He looks even weirder than
the IP address. And honestly,
he's a pretty complex dude.
We're gonna spend a lot of time getting
to know this guy in this series,
but real quick, can I show you a hack?
That's gonna save you like a
billion hours. Now notice that Mr.
Subnet mask does look pretty
similar to the IP address.
He's got four sets of
numbers and three dots.
And if you assume that the first number
in the IP address matches up to the
first number in the subnet mask,
you'd be exactly right. In fact,
they all match up two to two to
three to three, four to four.
Now here comes the hack. When you see
2 55 in an OCTE, which by the way,
each of these sections separated
by a dot, we call them octets.
We will dive deeper into why we
call them that. And yeah, it's,
it's gonna get a lot more nerdy and so
much more fun. I can't tell you more.
Just know they're called octets for
now. Just calm down. So anyways,
back to the hack, if
that number is a 2 55,
then we know that the corresponding number
or the corresponding OCTE will always
stay the same within your network. That
is so looking at our subnet mask here,
we know the first three octets. So
the first three numbers are 2 55,
which tells us that the first three
numbers in P address 1 9, 2, 1 6, 8,
and one will always stay
the same in our network.
We can confidently say that every single
device in your network at your house or
your business, if they look like this,
they're gonna start with 1 9 2 1 6 8 1.
And that brings us to the
last number over here,
the zero what's this guy doing
this zero is telling us that, Hey,
this slot last number, it
can be whatever you want,
whatever your heart's desire, as
long at just between zero and 2 55,
but still whatever you want, you
can use. 'em all. So to sum it up,
when you see a 2 55, that number's locked
in, these numbers will never change,
but the zero tells us the
final number totally will,
based on what device it's assigned to.
So if you'll allow me to get a bit nerdier
and go a bit deeper in the networking
world,
we refer to these numbers right here as
the network portion of the IP address.
And then on this side,
the side that'll change based
on what device it's assigned to.
We call that the host portion because
in networking and it, in general,
when we have devices on a network,
your phone, your watch, your toilet,
we call those hosts. Your toilet is a
host and it has an IP address. Now what?
I just put that in your pocket. Don't let
nobody hack it. This will become very,
very important later, but now
let me ask you a question.
Why is it important that we have to know
the network portion of the IP address?
Why do we have to know that
the IP addresses in our
network start with 1 92 0.1
6, 8 1 analogy time. We can
also think about an IP address,
like the address of our house. Like, you
know, the place you and tell you what,
why don't you comment below your
home address? I'm totally kidding.
Don't do that. Are you crazy?
Don't do that. But anyways,
you live in a house in that
house. Most of the time,
I think always is going
to be on a street, right?
And let's say your street that
you live on is private drive.
If you know where that's from,
comment below and because you're probably
not the only house on private drive,
you can't just say, Hey, send
me a edge on private drive.
I live on private drive.
Oh, houses need windows.
I know it looked kind of weird. Hold on,
let me draw some windows. So anyways,
we'll assign a unique house number to you.
So you might live at four private drive
and your buddy might live at five and
then six and then 7, 8,
9. You got it. Right?
So if I were to send you
some network check coffee,
it would go to four private drive.
So I sent you some coffee and it was so
can dang delicious that you wanted to
bring some over to your friend, your
buddy Bernard, over at six private drive.
There's Bernard, no hang tight.
Here's where the analogy comes
into play with IP addresses.
So would you call ups and say, Hey, I
have some coffee. I wanna give Bernard,
come pick it up and take it to
Bernard. No. Now why would you do that?
Bernard lives on your same street.
So as you're preparing to send Bernard
some coffee, you would go, oh, Hey,
Bernard lives on private drive.
Therefore I can just walk outside and
hand it to him because we're so stinking
close. We're in the same street.
We're in the same neighborhood.
So if you're tracking with me
here, this analogy feels weird.
I don't know why is it
me? It's probably me.
If you're tracking with me the
network portion of our IP address,
the thing that stays the same
is akin to private drive and
the host portion.
The thing that does change is the
house address the house number four,
or it could be five,
or it could be six based on who you're
sending it to with our devices in our
network. It's the same for,
if you wanna share a picture
from your phone to your computer,
your phone will look at the IP address
of the computer and go, oh, Hey, yo,
we're on the same network. 1 92,
1 68, 1 he's in my neighborhood.
I can just walk over and give it to him.
But now let's say that the
coffee's really, really,
really good and Bernard wants
to send it to his buddy. Dr.
Strange over here on Bleecker
street. So Bernard and looks at Dr.
Strange's address. And he goes,
okay. He Bleecker, I can't say it.
Bleecker street. I don't
live on Bleecker street.
I can't just walk outside and hand
coffee to Dr. Strange. In fact,
he lives all the way in New York. He's
far away or maybe another dimension.
I don't know what what's going on.
So Bernard realizing he needs help.
We'll just call ups and have them
come pick it up and take coffee to Dr.
Strange. And in the same way, my
laptop may wanna out to netflix.com,
which has this IP address. And it's
in a completely different network.
And my laptop will go, dude.
He's not in my network.
He's not in my same
neighborhood. I need some help.
I need to call ups except in
this scenario, it's not ups.
It's miss default gateway or
miss default router, AKA router,
your computer or any on your network
will look at it's IP address.
And then look at Mr.
Subnet mask and go, huh?
My network is 1 9, 2, 1 60 eight.one.
Netflix is not in my neighborhood.
I need help. Please help me. Miss
default, gateway, miss default gateway.
She knows everything.
She knows exactly how to get to Netflix
and she'll take it from there off on
fact, miss default gateway.
She's actually your router.
She's Oprah. I know mind blown the
entire time. Never saw it coming.
What a plot twist. That's some Scooby do
stuff right there. So sum that part up.
Whenever any device in your network,
whether it's your home network
or network at a business,
or pretty much any network in the world
when it wants to talk to something,
not on its same street and it wants to
talk to something outside its network.
It has to talk to its router.
It's default gateway to get out.
It has to talk to Oprah. Write
that down now real quick.
I got a challenge question for you. Let's
see if you've been paying attention,
looking at my network here, which might
be the exact same as your network.
I told you, this is one of the
most common networks in the world,
or did I tell you that? By the way,
this is one of the most
common networks in the world.
My kid just screamed for private networks,
looking at this IP address and
looking at this subnet mask.
How many possible IP addresses are
available to assign to devices in your
network? And by the way, if
you could figure this out,
that pretty much covers
the majority of networks.
I'm not sure what the statistics are,
but I think like network Chuck's opinion,
like 95% of all networks
kind of look like this.
So go ahead and comment your answer
below just raw, without me telling you,
I'm curious what it will be,
but let's walk through it real quick
and you're probably wrong. Sorry.
Looking at this, we know 2 55 and the
sub mask means this number locked in,
stays the same. So does this one
and this one because of the 2 55,
but over here is zero.
We know this last number can be
anything as long as it's between
zero and 255, which would give us a total,
including zero of 256 IP
addresses party. We get a ton,
but you're wrong. It's not 250 E
six because like everything in life,
there's a catch. There's always
tax. There's always extra fees.
You always have to look for that
life lesson. Anyways, here we go.
Where's the catch. Where's the extra fees
in our networking. Well, first of all,
right off the bat, there are always
two IP addresses that are reserved,
that you cannot touch. You cannot use.
And any given network first it's the
first IP address and your network.
So in this one, it would be 1 92 do
1 68, 1 0 that one's untouchable.
It's referred to as the network
address. He's a leader. He's the first,
the firstborn son. You can't touch him.
The second IP address you can't touch
is the last IP address in your network.
And this particular network
we're talking about.
It'd 1 92, 1 6, 8, 1 dot 2 55. This guy,
dude, he talks way much.
He's a chatty, Kathy.
We call him the broadcast address
because when you tell him something,
he tells it to everyone. Can't keep a
secret. And that's legit what he does.
When you send anything to a broadcast
address, the last IP address, any network,
it literally will broadcast it out to
everybody. It's like, Hey everyone,
guess what? So don't tell him anything
unless you want everyone to know.
So that's two, you can't touch. And
then one you really have to think about,
and it might just be this default
gateway. There has to be a router. Oh,
I just drove over that.
There has to be a router in your network
and that will take up one IP address.
So we're now three IP
addresses shy of 256,
which gives us a total of
250 free usable IP addresses.
If you got that right, you're on your
way to becoming a subnetting master.
Congrats. If you didn't,
that's totally okay.
This is so brand new and can be
very complex, but don't worry.
We're gonna hold hands. No, I'm gonna
hold your hand and walk you through this.
So little coffee break. We
covered so much in this video.
Oh, that's cold coffee.
That's how long I've been here recording
it's cold coffee. Like the video.
Cause I just sip some cold coffee. I, I,
ah, I need to heat it up, but anyways,
let's take a look. What we've
covered so far in this video,
we talked about IP addresses, right? We
talked about that. Everything in your,
your network,
in your house that wants to connect and
talk either to other devices in your
network or two devices outside
the network on the internet,
Netflix or just your toilet, having
a conversation with your watch.
If any of that needs to happen,
you have to have an IP address,
basically the cell phone
number of your devices,
unless you actually have a cell phone.
Then it also has a cell phone number
and an IP address. Very confusing.
I know Chuck get better at analogies.
You also get a chance to meet Mr. Subnet,
a very complex and mysterious dude.
You'll get to know a lot
better in the coming videos.
He also goes by net mask and he tells
us and our devices what our IP addresses
and our entire network start with.
He tells us what street we live on.
And this network right here,
this street we live on is 1 90, 2 60
eight.one because of our little hack,
the 2 55 S then finally you
met miss default gateway,
AKA default router or router
or Oprah. She does it all.
Not only does she give all your
devices in your network N IP address,
but she could help you
get outside your network.
If you wanna go visit Netflix or network,
check.com or even better network,
chuck.coffee. So anyways,
that's IP addresses and I just
realized I spelled IP address wrong.
Let's add the extra D cool. We're
good. And lemme tell you, yes,
we are just scratching the service.
We're gonna get much more complex on
how IP addresses work in the world
and, and your home network
and in your business.
And you'll learn that killer
skill, that crazy awesome,
old that you pretty much need
for anything in it. Subnetting,
because let me tell you, this example
we've been working with here is very,
very simple, but don't you worry.
You're gonna learn the skills to
make this crazy complex and fun.
And by the end, you will be a
master chief ninja subnet master.
Did I say master twice? That's fine.
This video is sponsored by manscaped.
Hold on. Let me make sure
there's no one listening on beer.
We should be good. No little ears
out there. All right. Listen up men.
This ad is for you cuz
I got some new toys.
So as you may recall from my last ad or
maybe other ads manscape is all about
stuff below the waist for men. Uh, yeah.
It's trusted over 4 million men to
make sure everything downstairs is
looking good. Smelling. Good,
good. Now manscape is going,
um,
beyond the groin with the
brand new lineup of products,
they're calling this the manscaped
ultra premium collection,
all those really big words.
This is an all in one skin care kit so
they can got stuff for your skin and for
your hair. That's pretty good.
Got some shampoo and body wash.
And this is the, the newest
formulations by manscape for your, uh,
your butt balls and
body all in one package.
The reason these ads are so awkward.
All right, so they, they have steps.
What do you say? We give it a
try. Let's do this step one.
I'll hop in the shower and use the
two in one shampoo and conditioner,
which cleanses in nourishes with a
luxurious lather. It's got coconut walk,
green tea, Allo Ric and Sage feels
nice. Step two, we got the body wash.
The body Washe is a premium daily shower
gel that's infused with Alovera and
sea. It's the perfect balance of tough,
clean and soothing hydration. Step three,
we're gonna RINs and towel off and then
apply something I've never seen before.
Manscaped hydrating body spray. It's
a spray on moisturizer for everyday.
Hydration is what it says. Got a
360 degree delivery spray system.
And no we're not done yet. Step four, we
got deodorant smells pretty dang good.
This stuff is stain
free. Aluminum free eyes.
Clear smells fricking fantastic. And
now type for step five manscape lip Bal.
You've probably never seen
my lips. They're there,
but my wife says I don't have any.
It's got vitamin E peppermint
and eucalyptus to help soothe,
hydrate and seal in moisture. All this
stuff is cruelty free, Paran free.
And it's vegan now was
five steps, five minutes.
Although I like to take
my showers a bit longer.
So 10 minutes you can also opt in for
the manscaped, uh, peak hygiene plan.
So you can make sure you never
run outta stuff. Cuz you know,
I don't like going to the store,
just pick a plan and that
stuff gets delivered to you
without you thinking about
it. So you can focus on studying
and IP, addressing and stuff,
go to manscape.com and use promo code
network chucking at 20% off your order
plus receive free international
shipping. And yeah,
that was 20% off with free international
shipping with promo code network,
chuck@manscape.com or just
click the link below. Thank you.
Manscaped for covering me
head to toe and seriously,
thanks for sponsoring the video.
You guys should get the
stuff cuz you sting you.
That's all I have explaining
IP addressing is not easy.
So let's make sure you hack
the YouTube algorithm today.
If that light button subscribe
notification bell comment,
we gotta hack YouTube today.
Ethically of course. And yeah,
that's really all I got. Whew,
I'll get you guys next time.